AXIOM computes STEM answers with deterministic code,
then uses OpenAI only to explain the verified result.
This is the primary demo: a single-gene genetics cross, Aa times aa.
Before any AI text appears, AXIOM enumerates the exact two-by-two Punnett grid.
The genotype probabilities, fifty percent Aa, fifty percent aa,
come from direct enumeration, not from a language model.
The result is packaged as stable facts and steps.
Each one has an ID, like genetics-dot-probability-dot-Aa.
Those are the only evidence IDs the explanation is allowed to cite.
On the server, AXIOM recomputes the deterministic result,
sends that record to OpenAI, validates the JSON, and verifies every claim.
OpenAI adapts the wording to the learner's level and language,
it does not recalculate the cross.
Citation chips link each sentence back to the evidence ledger.
A green Verified badge means every citation is valid
and every number is in the deterministic allowlist.
If a citation is missing, a number changes,
or the model output is malformed, AXIOM honestly shows Warnings
or Could not verify.
AXIOM also ships a chat interface.
Ask Aa times aa or C-of-ten-three in plain text,
the same deterministic engine answers, with the same verification badge.
No API key? The flow still works:
AXIOM shows a clearly labeled deterministic fallback.
Compute first. Explain with citations. Verify every claim.
That's AXIOM.